export default  G6_English_Ministry_2015 = [
  {
      id: "h1",
      Number_of_Questions: "40 Questions",
      // Time_Allowed: "1 hour",
    },
    {
      id: 'h2',
      header1: "Grade 6 English Ministry Exam "
    },
    {
      id: "I",
      header1: "My Family",
     
    },
    {
      id: 'p1',
      passage: "This is my family. My mother is a teacher. She teaches English language at primary school in the town we live. She has got a big eyes and long hair. She is beautiful. My father is businessman. He works in his own company. He has a shoe factory. He is tall. He has brown eyes. He is handsome. \n" +
      "I have got two sisters. Their names are Hanna and Aster. They have long black hair and big eyes like my mother. I love them a lot. And, we have a pet. It is a cat. It has got long tail and orange eyes. My family is amazing."
    },
    {
      id: 1,
      question: "Who is the teacher?",
      options: [" mother", " father","Hanna","Aster"],
      correct_option: "mother",
      explanation: "The passage states that the mother is a teacher."
    },
    {
      id: 2,
      question: "The Father is_________",
      options: [" teacher", " businessman","beautiful","short"],
      correct_option: "businessman",
      explanation: "The passage mentions the father's profession as a businessman."
    },
    {
      id: 3,
      question: "How many children are there in the family?",
      options: [" one", " two", " Three", " five"],
      correct_option: " Three",
      explanation: "The passage mentions two sisters, Hanna and Aster and the writer him/herself"
    },
    {
      id: 4,
      question: "Who loves his sisters a lot?",
      options: [" the father", " the mother", " the sisters", " the writer"],
      correct_option: " the writer",
      explanation: "The passage uses phrases like 'my mother' and 'my sisters,' indicating the writer is talking about their own family."
    },
    {
      id: 5,
      question: "According to the passage, which one is a true statement?",
      options: [
        " Hanna and Aster are students in the primary school.",
        " The mother and father work in their own company.",
        " The writer of this story has got two sisters.",
        "  The cat has got long hair."
      ],
      correct_option: " The writer of this story has got two sisters.",
      explanation: "Only option C directly matches information from the passage. While it's likely Hanna and Aster are students (given their age and the mother's profession), the passage doesn't explicitly state it. There's no mention of the parents working together, and the cat's hair length isn't described."
    },
    { 
      id: "II",
      header1: "Grammar",
      header2: "Directions: For items 6-19 choose the correct alternative that answers the question.",
    },
    {
      id: 6,
      question: "Hikma_____ in library every Tuesday and Thursday afternoon.",
      options: [" reading", " reads", " will read", " was read"],
      correct_option: " reads",
      explanation: "The present tense 'reads' indicates a habitual action that happens regularly."
    },
    {
      id: 7,
      question: "Coffee______ in Jimma by the local farmers.",
      options: [" grows", " is grown", "  is growing", "  growing"],
      correct_option: " is grown",
      explanation: "The passive voice 'is grown' indicates that the action is done to the coffee by the farmers."
    },
    {
      id: 8,
      question: "Students _______respect their teachers.",
      options: [" are", " may", " must", " should not"],
      correct_option: "must",
      explanation: "Must emphasizes the idea of obligation or necessity"
    },
    {
      id: 9,
      question: "If you_______hard, you would answer all the questions.",
      options: [" Will study", "  Would study", " study", " studied"],
      correct_option: "studied",
      explanation: "in second conditional sentences we use the simple past tense in the if-clause and a modal auxiliary verb (e.g., could, should, would, might) in the main clause."
    },
    {
      id: 10,
      question: "My sister______ to Canada three years ago.",
      options: [" went", " goes", " will go", "  is going"],
      correct_option: " went",
      explanation: "This sentence is talking about a past event."+
      "The past simple tense 'went' indicates a completed action in the past."
    },
    {
      id: 11,
      question: "Geremew is________ than Fekede. He height 74 ms, but Fekede heigh 45 ms",
      options: [" taller", " more taller", " tall", " tallest"],
      correct_option: " taller",
      explanation: "The comparative adjective 'taller' is used to compare two people."
    },
    {
      id: 12,
      question: "I can't go for a walk with you now. I am busy. I______my homework.",
      options: [" am", " am done", " did", " am doing"],
      correct_option: " am doing",
      explanation: `It uses the present continuous tense "am doing" to indicate an ongoing action that is happening at the moment of speaking:`
    },
    {
      id: 13,
      question: "He bought a sheep. \"Sheep\" is______",
      options: [" Proper noun", " abstract noun", "Common noun", " concrete noun"],
      correct_option: "Common noun",
      explanation: "Proper noun: refers to specific names of people, places, or things."+
      "For example, John, London, and Microsoft are proper nouns. "+
     "Abstract noun: refers to ideas, concepts, or qualities that cannot be perceived by the senses."+
     "Examples include love, happiness, and justice."+
      "Common noun: refers to general, non-specific names for people, places, or things."+
      "Examples include dog, table, and book. Sheep falls under this category, as it refers to a type or category of animal."+
      "Concrete noun: refers to tangible, physical objects that can be perceived by the senses."+
      "Examples include chair, tree, or car."
    },
    {
      id: 14,
      question: "Simegn______ wears trousers. But, today, she is wearing a dress.",
      options: ["sometimes", " usually", " once a week", " every day"],
      correct_option: " usually",
      explanation: `"Sometimes" indicates an unspecified frequency, but it doesn't convey the regularity implied in the sentence. \n`+
     `"Once a week" specifies a frequency of once per week, which is not suitable given the context of the sentence. \n`+
      `"Every day" indicates an action that happens daily, which contradicts the statement that she's wearing a dress today instead of trousers.\n`+
      `"Usually" best fits the context of the sentence. It indicates that wearing trousers is the common or typical behavior for Simegn, but it allows for exceptions, as seen today when she's wearing a dress.`
    },
    {
      id: 15,
      question: "I_______a car if I won ten million birr in the national lottery.",
      options: [" bought", " buy", " will buy", " would buy"],
      correct_option: "would buy",
      explanation: "Please Refer Question 9"
    },
    {
      id: 16,
      question: "If I had watched the movie, I _______ you the story.",
      options: [" would have told", " would tell", " will tell", " had told"],
      correct_option: " would have told",
      explanation: "The type 3 conditional is used to refer to an unreal past condition and its probable past result. In type 3 conditional sentences, the if clause uses the past perfect, and the main clause uses the perfect conditional."
    },
    {
      id: 17,
      question: "There is no enough vegetable at home. I hope my mother ______ some more in the coming days.",
      options: [" Will buy", " bought", "  was buying", " was bought"],
      correct_option: "Will buy",
      explanation: "The sentence expresses a future hope. 'Will buy' indicates an action your mother might take in the future."
    },
    {
      id: 18,
      question: "I don't see my father today. I guess he _____ go out to visit his friends.",
      options: [" will", "  must", " may", " can"],
      correct_option: " may",
      explanation: "We're unsure but making a guess about your father's action. 'May' expresses possibility."
    },
    {
      id: 19,
      question: "At the age of 3 and 4, I now I ________ cry when my mom gets out of home. But Now I don't do that.",
      options: [" am going", " used to", "  was", " am"],
      correct_option: " used to",
      explanation: "The sentence describes a past habit that no longer applies in the present. 'Used to' indicates that you cried in the past."
    },
    { 
      id: "III",
      header1: "III: Speaking",
      header2: "Directions: Items 20-26 are dialogues. Choose the correct alternative to complete the dialogue meaningfully."
      
    },
    {
      id: 20,
      question: 
      "Lula: Hello! Good to meet you."+
       "Rahel: Hello!________",
              options: [
        " I'm fine, thank you.",
        " What is your name?",
        " Good morning Rahel.",
        " Good to meet you, too."
      ],
      correct_option: " Good to meet you, too.",
      explanation: `"Good to meet you, too." It acknowledges Lula's statement and reciprocates the sentiment.`
    },
    {
      id: 21,
      question: "Henock: which do you like better, Summer or Winter?"+
                "Senayit:_____________________________.The Weather is good in summer season.",
      options: [
        " I don't like summer",
        "  Summer is bad season",
        " I like summer",
        " I dislike summer"
      ],
      correct_option: " I like summer",
      explanation:  "It directly answers Henock's question and aligns with Senayit's subsequent statement about the good weather in summer."
    },
    {
      id: 22,
      question: "Friend: what does you mother looks like?"+
                "You:___________________________________",
      options: [
        " She is a nurse.",
        " She speaks English.",
        " She has two brothers.",
        " She is tall and beautiful."
      ],
      correct_option: " She is tall and beautiful.",
      explanation: " This option directly answers the question by describing your mother's physical appearance."
    },
    {
      id: 23,
      question: "Nardos: What do you think about air pollution."+
                "Yohannes:__________________________________",
      options: [
        " I like my school.",
        " I think it is bad.",
        " What is air pollution?",
        " Good morning Yohannes."
      ],
      correct_option: "I think it is bad.",
      explanation: " This option directly answers Nardos's question by expressing Yohannes's opinion about air pollution."
    },
    {
      id: 24,
      question: "Friend: Money is better than knowledge."+
               "You:______________________. It is less important",
      options: [
        " I don't agree",
        " That is true",
        " I agree with you",
        " You are correct"
      ],
      correct_option: "I don't agree",
      explanation:"I don't agree. This option expresses disagreement with the statement made by the friend, which aligns with the speaker's response."
    },
    {
      id: 25,
      question: "Your friend: I've got a bad toothache. What do you advise me to do?"+
                "You:______________________________________",
                 options: [
        " You are a grade 6 student",
        " You should stop eating sweets",
        " Where is the clinic?",
        " I totally disagree with you."
      ],
      correct_option: "You should stop eating sweets",
      explanation:`The response "You should stop eating sweets" suggests a possible cause for the toothache. Eating sweets can contribute to tooth decay and cavities, which can lead to toothaches.`+
      " Therefore, advising your friend to cut back on sweets may help alleviate the pain and prevent future toothaches."
    },
    {
      id: 26,
      question: "Guest: How can I get to the hospital please?"+
                "Police officer:_________________________. You will see it there",
      options: [
        " Go straight along this way. Then turn left at the crossroad.",
        " Take care. There are many thieves.",
        " What can I help you please?",
        " Thank you very much."
      ],
      correct_option: "Go straight along this way. Then turn left at the crossroad.",
      explanation:'The response "Go straight along this way. Then turn left at the crossroad. You will see it there." provides clear and precise directions to the hospital.' +
      "It instructs the guest to continue straight ahead on the current path and then make a left turn at the crossroad. "
    },
    { 
      id: "IV",
      header1: "IV: Vocabulary",
      header2: "Directions: For items 27 and 28 choose the word which is similar meaning with the word written in bold.",
    },
    {
      id: 27,
      question: `Adane scored three goals in the match. His role was "vital" to win. What is the synonym for 'vital' in this context?`,
      options: [" dangerous", " important", " small", "bad"],
      correct_option: " important",
      explanation: "Vital means 'essential' or 'crucial' for success. 'Important' is the closest synonym in this context."
    },
    {
      id: 28,
      question: `Please "obey" the traffic rules. Cross on the zebra lines when the lights are red. What is the opposite of 'obey' in this context?`,
      options: [" follow", " forget", " break", " write"],
      correct_option: "break",
      explanation: "Obeying means following the rules. Breaking the rules is the opposite."
    },
    { 
      id: "V",
      // header1: "IV: Vocabulary",
      header2: "Directions: For items 29 and 30 choose the word which completes the blank space.",
    },
    {
      id: 29,
      question: "As it rained well last week, farmers have started to _______ their farm lands. What word best describes the action farmers are taking after the rain?",
      options: [" harvest", " grow", " crop", " plough"],
      correct_option: " plough",
      explanation: "Harvesting is collecting crops"+
      "growing refers to the entire process"+
      "cropping can have different meanings"+
      "ploughing is preparing the land for planting after rain."
    },
    {
      id: 30,
      question: "Waste product that comes from factories should be managed carefully to avoid environmental___________",
             options: [" growth", " science", " pollution", "  production"],
      correct_option: " pollution",
      explanation: `The term "environmental pollution" refers to the introduction of harmful substances or contaminants into the natural environment.`
    },
    { 
      id: "VI",
      header1: "V: Reading Comprehension 2",
      header2: "Direction: Items 31 - 35 are based on the reading text below. Read it carefully and choose the correct alternative.",
    },
    {
      id: 'p1',
      header1: "Insects",
      passage: "Insects are a kind of animal. Insects can be found all over the world."+
      "Ants, grasshoppers, butterflies, and bees are some common insects.\n" +
      
      "Insects are invertebrates, so they do not have backbones. They have exoskeletons. This means they have their bones on the outside, like a shell. Some insects, like butterflies, can change as they grow. \n" +
      "Insects always have six legs. If something has eight legs, like a spider, it is not an insect. \n" +
      "Insects usually have three body parts. The head is where the eyes, mouth and brains are. The thorax is where the legs and wings connect. The abdomen is where the guts and organs are."
      
    },
    {
      id: 31,
      question: "Which one is an example of an insect?",
      options: [" spider", " ostrich", " butterfly", " snake"],
      correct_option: "butterfly",
      explanation: "Butterflies are insects, while spiders, ostriches, and snakes belong to different animal groups."
    },
    {
      id: 32,
      question: "Which one is true about insects?",
      options: [" are not animal", " have more than six legs", " have backbones", " are found everywhere"],
      correct_option: " are found everywhere",
      explanation: "Insects are animals, typically have six legs (not more), lack backbones, and are widely distributed on Earth."
    },
    {
      id: 33,
      question: "How many legs do insects have?",
      options: [" eight", " six", " three", " four"],
      correct_option: " six",
      explanation: "Insects are characterized by having six legs."
    },
    {
      id: 34,
      question: "The correct order of insects' body parts in the passage is_",
      options: [" Thorax - head - abdomen", " Head - thorax – abdomen", " Thorax - abdomen- head", " Abdomen - head - thorax"],
      correct_option: " Head - thorax – abdomen",
      explanation: "The typical body structure of an insect involves the head, thorax (containing legs and wings), and abdomen (containing digestive and reproductive organs)."
    },
    {
      id: 35,
      question: "What are invertebrates?",
      options: [" Animals with backbones", " Animals with wings", " Animals without backbones", " Animals with two legs"],
      correct_option: " Animals without backbones",
      explanation: "Invertebrates are a vast animal group defined by the absence of a backbone (spinal column). Insects fall under this category."
    },
    { 
      id: "VII",
      header1: "VI: Writing",
      header2: "Direction: Items 36 -40 are about writing skills. Choose the correct alternative accordingly.",
    },
    
    {
      id: 36,
      question: "Which one is a sentence?",
      options: [" English language", "  My father is", "  The book on the table", "  I read the book."],
      correct_option: " I read the book.",
      explanation: "A sentence expresses a complete thought and has a subject and a verb (or verb phrase)."
    },
    {
      id: 37,
      question: "\"Solomon likes fruits, but Beza likes vegetables.\" This is__________",
      options: [" Simple sentence", " Complex sentence", " Compound sentence", " Compound complex sentence"],
      correct_option: "  Compound sentence",
      explanation: "A compound sentence combines two or more independent clauses using a coordinating conjunction (but in this case). A simple sentence has one independent clause, a complex sentence has one independent clause and one dependent clause, and a compound-complex sentence has two or more independent clauses and at least one dependent clause."
    },
    {
      id: 38,
      question: "\"Helen is very beautiful. She has a long nose, big eyes and long hair. Also she is tall.\" This is an example of___________",
      options: ["  Descriptive writing", " Narrative writing", "  Argumentative writing", " Expository writing."],
      correct_option: " Descriptive writing",
      explanation: "Descriptive writing focuses on using vivid language to create a picture in the reader's mind. This passage describes Helen's physical appearance."
    },
    {
      id: 39,
      question: "Which one is a correctly written sentence?",
      options: [" I have two brothers.", " Two brothers have I.", " Brothers I two have.", " I two have brothers."],
      correct_option: " I have two brothers.",
      explanation: "A proper sentence follows subject-verb order (I) and avoids unnecessary inversion (B, C, D)."
    },
    {
      id: 40,
      question: "\"We visited Unity Park yesterday. First, we visited different wild animals in the zoo. Then, we visited the palace.\" This is an Example of___________",
      options: [" Descriptive writing", " Expository writing", " Argumentative writing", " Narrative writing"],
      correct_option: " Narrative writing",
      explanation: "Narrative writing tells a story with a sequence of events. This passage describes a visit to Unity Park with a clear timeline."
    }


]